Dorothy Reed Mendenhall Papers, 1805-2003
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL 1874-2003
  - Education
    - Smith College
      - Diploma 1895
        [see OVERSIZE MATERIALS]
      - Honorary Doctorate: correspondence, diploma map, program, and song 1929-30 (Box 3, Folder 9)
        [see also OVERSIZE MATERIALS]
      - Printed material: catalog and songbook 1894-95 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Massachusetts Institute of Technology: correspondence and grades 1895-96 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Johns Hopkins University Medical School
      - General: correspondence, newspaper clippings, printed material 1894-1947 (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - Lecture notes 1896-1900 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Drawings 1896-1900 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Diploma 1900
  - Professional credentials
    - Physician's license, state of New York 1902 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Physicians license, state of Wisconsin 1916
  - Certificate of appointment as a delegate for the state of Wisconsin to the Annual Meeting of the Child Hygiene Association 1920 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Certificate of appointment as U.S. delegate to the Fifth English-speaking Conference on Maternity and Child Welfare in London, issued by the U.S. State Department in Apr. 1929
  - Legal documents
    - Passports 1926, 1929 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Wills 1936-50 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Financial documents
    - Account books 1890-98, 1930 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Travel receipts 1938-41, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Personal records
    - Calendars 1953-55 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Childhood writings and sketches: drawings, notes, poems, and themes 1886, 1890, undated (Box 5, Folder 5-6)
    - Contacts: address book and notes undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Diaries 1890-94, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Garden notebook 1939-50 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Invitations and party lists 1906-50 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Medical records: correspondence, prescription, and receipt 1910-36 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Memberships 1892-1928, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Notes and lists
      - T.S. Eliot: newspaper clippings and notes 1949, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - Rudyard Kipling: newspaper clippings, notes, and themes undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - Miscellaneous notes undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Prayers 1907-55 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Memorabilia: business cards, drawings, garden plan, hair, hymnal, invitations, menus, notes, programs, and ration books 1896-40s, undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Photographs
    - DRM alone
      - Youth 1879-93 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - Adulthood (including photo of bust sculpted by Joy Buba) 1894-1967, undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Family
      - Individuals
        - Baker, Laura Ann undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
        - Furbish, Elizabeth Reed undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
        - Kimball, Carroll undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
        - Kimball, Eliza undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
        - Kimball, Hannibal undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
        - Mendenhall, Bethany at three months 1940 (Box 7, Folder 3)
        - Mendenhall, Charles E. circa 1882-1920s (Box 7, Folder 3)
        - Mendenhall, Richard 1911 (Box 7, Folder 3)
        - Reed, Grace Kimball 1895 (Box 7, Folder 3)
        - Reed, William Pratt circa 1850, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
        - Talcott, Adaline undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
        - Talcott, Hezekiah undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
      - Groups
        - Baker, Adaline, Rosalind, Helen, and Laura, with Lodemia Talcott undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
        - DRM and Elizabeth Reed circa 1888 (Box 7, Folder 4)
        - DRM and Dorothy Reed Furbish 1900-05 (Box 7, Folder 4)
        - DRM with Charles/Thomas/John Mendenhall 1906-61 (Box 7, Folder 4)
        - Thomas and John Mendenhall with 4 unidentified people 30 May 1919 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Friends
      - Individuals
        - Austin, Mabel F., undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
        - Bigelow, Laura undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
        - MacCallum, William 1901 (Box 7, Folder 5)
        - Boem, Caroline Mitchell undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
        - Lathrop, Julia undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
        - Long, Margaret, circa 1890s and undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
        - Strong, Mary, 1905 (Box 7, Folder 5)
        - Woods, Eleanor Bush, 1896 (Box 7, Folder 5)
      - Groups
        - DRM with Smith College friends, 1893-1900 (Box 8, Folder 1)
        - DRM and others on a walking trip in New York state during medical school, circa late 1890s (Box 8, Folder 1)
        - DRM with Miss Wheeler, Atlantic City, 1904 (Box 8, Folder 1)
        - DRM with unidentified man, circa 1904 (Box 8, Folder 1)
        - DRM with three unidentified people standing in front of car, 1929 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Hospital scenes
      - Brooklyn Naval Hospital, DRM with Margaret Long and others, 1898 (Box 8, Folder 2)
      - Johns Hopkins Hospital
        - House staff, 1901 (Box 8, Folder 2)
        - Operating room staff, circa 1900 (Box 8, Folder 2)
        - Miscellaneous staff and patients, circa 1900 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Residences
      - Kimball estate, undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
      - Talcottville house
        - Exterior, undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
        - North parlor, circa 1900 (Box 8, Folder 3)
        - Falls, undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
      - Room in Wallace House at Smith College, 1893 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous and unidentified
      - Elizabeth Blackwell (photo of drawing), 1951 (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - U.S. Navy ship "Dolphin," undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - Unidentified people standing at bow of ship, undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - Unidentified, undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
- SERIES II. FAMILY 1805-1938
  - Genealogical material: notes, family trees, handwritten manuscript connecting DRM to Dudley and Bradstreet families undated (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
  - Individuals, [see also SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL-Photographs]
    - Elizabeth Reed Furbish (DRM's sister) and family: newspaper clippings, notes, and wedding invitations 1892-1924 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Adaline Talcott Kimball (DRM's maternal grandmother)
      - Correspondence 1831-50, undated (Box 9, Folder 4-6)
      - Poems and sketches 1825-37, undated (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Hannibal Kimball (DRM's maternal grandfather): correspondence 1829-62, undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Charles Elwood Mendenhall (DRM's husband): biographies, business cards, correspondence, diary, invitations, newspaper clippings, notes, travel descriptions, programs from memorial service, and wedding invitation 1884-1935 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - John Talcott Mendenhall (DRM's third son): hair clippings 1914 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Margaret Mendenhall (DRM's daughter): plaque 1907 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Richard Mendenhall (DRM's first son): newspaper clippings, notes, poem, and sympathy letters 1908-10 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Thomas Corwin Mendenhall Jr. (DRM's second son): hair clippings, newspaper clippings, poem and telegram 1911-38, undated (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Grace Kimball Reed (DRM's mother): correspondence, and wedding invitation 1867-81, undated (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - William Reed, Sr. (DRM's father): correspondence, family history, genealogical notes, journal, wallet, and wedding invitation 1858-72, undated (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - William Reed, Jr. and Gloria Reed (DRM's brother and sister-in-law): correspondence undated (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Talcott family papers
    - Correspondence 1833-1860 (Box 10, Folder 9-10)
    - Legal and financial records for Furbish/Kimball/Reed/Talcott estates: correspondence, deeds, investments, lists, mortgages, patent, plot plans, and receipts 1811-1930s, undated (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Miscellaneous: commissions, newspaper clippings, notes, petitions, school records, sewing pattern, and notes 1805-60, undated (Box 10, Folder 12)
- SERIES III. CORRESPONDENCE 1891-1962
  - Family
    - Furbish, Dorothy, Hart, and Ordway, 1911-57, undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Furbish, Elizabeth Reed, 1891-99, undated (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Mendenhall, Charles Elwood, 1901-35 (Box 11, Folder 3-4)
    - Mendenhall, Cornelia Baker, 1938-1960 (Box 11, Folder 5-8)
    - Mendenhall, John Talcott, 1919-45, 1957 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Mendenhall, Sally Cornell, 1946-49 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Mendenhall, Thomas, Sr. and Susan, 1911-23, undated (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Mendenhall, Thomas Corwin, Jr.
      - 1918-34 (Box 12, Folder 3-8)
      - 1935-43 (Box 13, Folder 1-9)
      - 1944-52 (Box 14, Folder 1-9)
      - 1953-62, 1960s, undated (Box 15, Folder 1-8)
    - Reed, Grace Kimball, 1896-1911 (Box 16, Folder 1-2)
    - Reed, William, Jr., 1892-1911 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Friends and Associates
    - General, (including sympathy letters after CEM's 1935 death), 1888-1960, undated (Box 16, Folder 4-7)
    - Individuals
      - Baldwin, Dr. J.F., 1900-01 (Box 17, Folder 1)
      - Bigelow, Sophia, 1936-56, undated (Box 17, Folder 2)
      - Cummings, Mabel, 1935-57 (Box 17, Folder 3)
      - Fast, Louisa K., 1897, 1927-35, undated (Box 17, Folder 4)
      - Hart, Merwin, 1918, 1935 (Box 17, Folder 5)
      - Hubbard, Lila M., 1891 (Box 17, Folder 6)
      - Kenyon, Josephine H., 1937 (Box 17, Folder 7)
      - Lamonte, Helen, 1932-50s (Box 17, Folder 8)
      - Lee, Laura Billings, 1902 (Box 17, Folder 9)
      - Long, John D., 1898 (Box 17, Folder 10)
      - Long, Margaret, 1898-1957 (Box 17, Folder 11)
      - MacCallum, William G., 1906, 1941, undated (Box 17, Folder 12)
      - Osler, William, 1900-04 (Box 17, Folder 13)
      - Pratt, Elsie Seelye, 1935-57 (Box 17, Folder 14)
      - Sharp, Bertha, 1936, undated (Box 17, Folder 15)
      - Smith, Dr. Mary A., 1902-03 (Box 17, Folder 16)
      - Thomas, M. Carey, 1901 (Box 17, Folder 17)
      - Welch, William, 1900-03 (Box 17, Folder 18)
      - Wilson, Edmund, 1955-57 (Box 17, Folder 19)
      - Young, Karl, 1930-35 (Box 17, Folder 20)
      - Other, undated (Box 17, Folder 21)
- SERIES IV. PROFESSIONAL MATERIAL 1898-1956
  - Babies Hospital of New York City: certificate of recognition, correspondence, formulary, lists, questionnaire, programs, and report 1903-37 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Brooklyn Naval Hospital: correspondence, endorsement, Hippocratic oath, newspaper clipping, notes, and photographs 1898 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Johns Hopkins University Hospital: correspondence, invitations, lists, notebook, notes, and prescriptions, 1900-02 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - United States Children's Bureau
    - Civil Service Commission ratings, 1917-31 (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence (includes Julia Lathrop, Grace Abbott, and Katharine Lenroot), 1917-32 (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - Printed material, 1919-49 (Box 18, Folder 6-8)
    - Proceedings of the Child Health Recovery Conference, Washington, D.C., 6 October 1933 (Box 18, Folder 9)
    - Miscellaneous: appointment letter, identification card, memoranda, newspaper clipping, notes, pass, printed material, and receipts, 1924-28, undated (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - University of Chicago: outlines, 1930s (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - University of Wisconsin
    - College of Agriculture, Extension Division, Home Study Course: instruction papers, 1915 (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - Department of Home Economics
      - Examinations, 1931-47 (Box 19, Folder 4)
      - Lectures, 1938-39 (Box 19, Folder 5)
      - Notes, 1926-45 (Box 19, Folder 6)
      - Syllabi, 1936-45 (Box 19, Folder 7)
    - Summer school: syllabi, 1930-37 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Utah State Agricultural College: correspondence, 1938 (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Visiting Nurse Association Child Health Centers
    - Correspondence, 1928-49 (Box 19, Folder 10-11)
    - Directory, 1949-50 (Box 19, Folder 12)
    - Minutes, 1933 (Box 19, Folder 13)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1948-50 (Box 19, Folder 14)
    - Recommendations, 1936, undated (Box 19, Folder 15)
    - Reports, 1925-50, undated (Box 19, Folder 16)
  - Wisconsin Board of Health: certificate of registration, growth chart, and printed material, 1934-56 (Box 19, Folder 17)
- SERIES V. PUBLICATIONS 1901-1937
  - "The Bacillus Pseudo-Tuberculosis Murium: Its Streptothrix Forms and Pathogenic Action," in Contributions to the Science of Medicine and Johns Hopkins Hospital Reports, Vol. ix 1901 drawings, photographs, and printed material (Box 19, Folder 18)
  - "A Case of Acute Lymphatic Leukaemia Without Enlargement of the Lymph Glands," American Journal of the Medical Sciences Oct 1902 drawings, photographs, and printed material (Box 19, Folder 19)
  - "On the Pathological Changes in Hodgkin's Disease with Special Reference to its Relation to Tuberculosis," in Johns Hopkins Hospital Reports, Vol. X, Nos. 3, 4, 5 1902: drawings, photographs, and printed material (Box 20, Folder 1-2)
  - "Work of the Extension Department in Educating the Mother Along the Lines of Prenatal Care and Infant Hygiene," Transactions Seventh Annual Meeting, American Association for the Study and Prevention of Infant Mortality, Milwaukee, 19-20 Oct 1916 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - "Bathing the Baby," and "Prenatal Care," University of Wisconsin University Extension Division pamphlets 1916 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - "List of Books and Pamphlets on Infant Welfare," with Elva L. Bascom, Wisconsin Library Commission, Madison, Wisconsin 1916 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Review of Louis Fischer's The Health Care of the Growing Child, Funk & Wagnalls Co, published in The Survey 19 August 1916 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - "Prenatal and Natal Conditions in Wisconsin," Wisconsin Medical Journal, Volume XV, No. 10 March 1917 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - "What to Feed the Children," with Amy L. Daniels, Extension Service of the College of Agriculture, University of Wisconsin April 1917, February 1924, June 1927, and June 1930 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - "Milk: The Indispensable Food for Children," U.S. Department of Labor, Children's Bureau 1918 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - "A Memorandum on Milk," American Journal of the Medical Sciences," Vol. CLVI, No. 5 Oct 1918 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - "Child Welfare and the Milk Problem," The Child (London), V. 9, No. 2 Nov 1918 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - "The Work of the Children's Bureau," Smith Alumnae Quarterly May 1919 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - "Minimum Standards of Prenatal Care: The Least a Mother Should Do Before Her Baby is Born," U.S. Department of Labor, Children's Bureau 1923 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - "Preventative Feeding for Mothers and Infants," Journal of Home Economics, Vol. 16, No. 10 October 1924 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - "Madison and Its Pre-School Day: The Results of a Study Under Parent-Teacher Auspices," Child Health Magazine Jan 1925 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - "What Builds Babies? The Pregnant Mother's Diet in the Pregnant and Nursing Periods," U.S. Department of Labor, Children's Bureau (1925, 1933): correspondence, drafts, notes, printed material 1925-33 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - "Milk: The Indispensable Food for Children," U.S. Department of Labor Children's Bureau Publication No. 163 1926 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - "What is Happening to Mothers and Babies in the District of Columbia," U.S. Department of Labor Children's Bureau 1928 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - "Midwifery in Denmark," U.S. Department of Labor, Children's Bureau, pamphlet (1929): contacts, correspondence, drafts, notes, tables, 1926-29 (Box 20, Folder 6-7)
  - "Hemoglobin Content of the Blood of Infants," with C.A. Elvehjem and W.H. Peterson, American Journal of Diseases of Children, Vol. 46 Jul 1933 (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - "Effect of Iron and Copper Therapy on Hemoglobin Content of the Blood of Infants," American Journal of Diseases of Children, Vol. 50 Jul 1935 (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - "Iron Versus Iron and Copper in the Treatment of Anemia in Infants," with C.A. Elvehjem and Dorothy Duckles, American Journal of Diseases of Children 1937 (Box 20, Folder 8)
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  - Smith College diploma and honorary doctorate diploma 1895, 1930 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Johns Hopkins University M.D. diploma1900 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Physician's license, state of Wisconsin1916 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Certificate of appointment as U.S. delegate to the Fifth English-speaking Conference on Maternity and Child Welfare in London, issued by the U.S. State DepartmentApr 1929 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Babies' Hospital of New York City Certificate of Recognition1906 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Medical drawingcirca 1900 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Watercolor of a tulip tree (Liriodendron tulipifera) flower and foliage1889 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - "Midwifery in Denmark": tablescirca 1929 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Advertisement for book of portraits: William H. Welch, "my patron saint" at Johns Hopkins Medical (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Talcott Family (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - Johnson Talcott: appointment as Cornet of 2nd Squadron of the 5th Division of the Cavalry of the State of New York 1809
    - Johnson Talcott: appointment as 1st Lieutenant of the 14th Regiment of the Cavalry of the State of New York 1817
    - Johnson Talcott: Abstract Inspection Return form for Cavalry regiment1818
    - Embroidery design
  - Talcott Family (Map-case Flate file, drawer 32)
    - License to produce in Conneticut water boiler and steam still, patented by Phares Bernard 3 May 1811
    - Maps: plots of Kimball property in Chattanooga, Tennessee
    - Garden design plan, by Josephine Osgood Morris1927